<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://patriciamcphee.github.io/portfolio/blog</id>
    <title>Patricia McPhee Blog</title>
    <updated>2022-03-04T12:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://patriciamcphee.github.io/portfolio/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Patricia McPhee Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://patriciamcphee.github.io/portfolio/img/favicon.png</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Technical Writing Demystified]]></title>
        <id>/2022/03/04/technical-writing-demystified</id>
        <link href="https://patriciamcphee.github.io/portfolio/blog/2022/03/04/technical-writing-demystified"/>
        <updated>2022-03-04T12:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Come back soon for the full article.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Come back soon for the full article.</p><p>Other articles I'm working on include: </p><ul><li>What's wrong with Technical Writer job descriptions</li><li>What technical writing is NOT!</li><li>Information architecture</li><li>Content strategy</li><li>Topic-based writing</li><li>Scenario and goal-based writing</li></ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Patricia McPhee</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/patriciamcphee</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="technical writing" term="technical writing"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[How much does quality content matter?]]></title>
        <id>/2022/02/18/how-much-does-quality-content-matter</id>
        <link href="https://patriciamcphee.github.io/portfolio/blog/2022/02/18/how-much-does-quality-content-matter"/>
        <updated>2022-02-19T11:41:21.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The quality of your organization's technical documentation matters now more than ever. I have found in my experience that potential customers also evaluate the technical documentation carefully before they buy. Whether they're an IT professional evaluating an enterprise application or a consumer using a product, they're reading your content to learn about the product and how to use it.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The quality of your organization's technical documentation matters now more than ever. I have found in my experience that potential customers also evaluate the technical documentation carefully before they buy. Whether they're an IT professional evaluating an enterprise application or a consumer using a product, they're reading your content to learn about the product and how to use it. </p><p>If your prospective customers cannot find high-quality technical or user documentation to support their purchase decisions, you may never have a chance to close the deal. </p><ul><li><p>Good informational content helps your prospects become customers. They want to understand your capabilities and unique value. </p></li><li><p>Good instructional content helps your customers <em>remain</em> your customers. They need fast, effective service. </p></li><li><p>Great technical documentation <em>empowers</em> the user. Not frustrate them. Plus, it's an integral part of customer support, branding, and trust. If it's not there for them, they start looking for alternatives.</p></li></ul><p>In this article, you'll learn about the costs and risks of content quality problems. You'll also learn how to course-correct and create a good experience for the user when using your product or service.  </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="costs-and-risks-of-content-quality-problems">Costs and risks of content quality problems<a class="hash-link" href="#costs-and-risks-of-content-quality-problems" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>There are several dimensions to good technical documentation:</p><ul><li><p>Can the reader find it and understand it?</p></li><li><p>Is the content complete and accurate?</p></li><li><p>Is there a consistent use of product branding and industry terminology? </p></li></ul><p>We can break these down further, but we'll stick with this high-level list for this article. </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="findable">Findable<a class="hash-link" href="#findable" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Today, it's more important to be able to search the content. In addition, technical documentation has evolved, especially over the past decade. Technical documentation is primarily in an online help format with an option to download a PDF version. With that said, SEO in technical documentation helps search engines respond with the most relevant content.</p><p>A great example of SEO in technical documentation comes from Microsoft. In their content, on docs.microsoft.com, the <code>description</code> metadata field is required and must follow the SEO writing guidelines. Microsoft develops its technical content using markdown in the Docfx ecosystem.</p><div class="codeBlockContainer_I0IT language-text theme-code-block"><div class="codeBlockContent_wNvx text"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-text codeBlock_jd64 thin-scrollbar" style="color:#393A34;background-color:#f6f8fa"><code class="codeBlockLines_mRuA"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">---</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">title: Manage Azure portal settings and preferences</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">description: Learn how to change Azure portal settings such as default subscription or directory, timeouts, menu mode, contrast, theme, notifications, language or region, and more.</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">date:  08/10/2021 </span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">topic: how-to</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">---</span><br></span></code></pre><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" class="copyButton_wuS7 clean-btn">Copy</button></div></div><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="accurate-and-complete">Accurate and complete<a class="hash-link" href="#accurate-and-complete" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Technical documentation is living content that is continuously updated as new features are released, or operational processes change. Because of this, it must be reviewed for accuracy and completeness. For example, is the expected behavior of the product feature accurately described? Are the procedural steps accurate and complete? </p><p>Accurate and complete means the user accomplished what they set out to do because the information was in the documentation. However, they're at a dead-end and left to call support if it's not there. </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="consistent">Consistent<a class="hash-link" href="#consistent" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>If your company has a valuable brand, you'll suffer a tangible loss if branding isn't used consistently. Inconsistencies can confuse users or affect the company's brand. For example, the user might be confused about which content is correct, mainly if your content uses several terms interchangeably. In addition, the translations by human and machine translators can contain these inconsistencies if your content is localized.       </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="understandable">Understandable<a class="hash-link" href="#understandable" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Even if the content is accurate, complete, and consistent, it might not be understood. This is because so many factors come into play when we talk about whether someone understands it or not:</p><ul><li><p><strong>Sentence structure</strong>: Does the sentence articulate the idea clearly and directly? Is the sentence so long it's too difficult to follow? Is the sentence too convoluted to understand? Does the sentence include information that adds nothing but confusion?</p></li><li><p><strong>Vocabulary</strong>: Does the user understand the words? Is your content translated?</p></li><li><p><strong>Terminology</strong>: Are the terms used correctly and consistently throughout the documentation? </p></li><li><p><strong>Spelling and grammar</strong>: Does the content contain relatively simple errors that distract, confuse, or mislead your readers?</p></li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="where-content-quality-problems-come-from">Where content quality problems come from<a class="hash-link" href="#where-content-quality-problems-come-from" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Content quality problems can come from different areas. I've observed that the audience is misunderstood—that is, the overall user journey is overlooked. For example, IT professionals are often misunderstood, so their content doesn't directly speak to them. What do I mean by this? Most often, the content is written by a very technical person, and then it's handed off for editing and formatting. There's rarely a discussion among the cross-functional teams on use cases or scenarios for the flow of the content, which would give the user what they need when they need it.  </p><p>I use the IT professional as an example because they have a hard job. Not one company has the same IT infrastructure implemented. So there's a lot on their plate with supporting different operating systems, versions of applications, security and preventing intrusions, user administration, and evaluating solutions. Because of this, I have found that writing content for them works best if it's in a scenario or goal-based format. The IT Professional consults technical documentation for a reason: get answers to their questions or implement an enterprise solution end-to-end. This format results in giving them what they need when they need it.</p><p>A survey conducted by the author and content strategist Rachel McConnel clearly recognized how quality content adds value. However, it also recognized the adverse business impact of letting just <em>anyone</em> create the content. But at the moment, it's still a blind spot for some organizations. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="how-to-design-and-develop-better-content">How to design and develop better content<a class="hash-link" href="#how-to-design-and-develop-better-content" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>In addition to the dimensions to good technical documentation mentioned earlier, you'll want to understand the user journey by "designing the content." Content design helps you develop better content because it answers a user's need in the best way to consume it. Sarah Winters states in her book that content design is "…about using data and evidence to give the audience what they need, at the time they need it and in a way they expect it." </p><p>Content design is not just writing. It's a way of thinking. It's collaborating with cross-functional teams like UX, product owners, and engineers to find the best solutions to give the user what they need when they need it and how they expect it. For example, the content could be a one-pager, a complete user guide, a training module, and so on. It could even be as small as UX/in-platform microcopy.</p><p>Creative director of A List Apart, Jeffrey Zeldman, stated in 2008:
Content precedes design. Design in the absence of content is not design, it's decoration.</p><p>The basic principle here is that user needs come first, then comes the format. You're creating content that helps create a good experience for the user when using your product or service. You're helping them along their journey!</p><p>Plain and simple: When you understand the user journey, you give them what they need when they need it and in the way they expect it.</p><p>We know that giving people information too early or in the wrong place can make people leave in frustration and no longer trust you. Understanding what your audience needs – when they need it – can be the difference between success and failure.</p><p>Use the language our users are using. You don't use language for search engines – you use it for the humans behind those engines. You don't pull people into useless pages. You help people. Language through a product must reflect your audience's vocabulary, or they may find the interaction too difficult and eventually abandon it.</p><p>In the end, once you have a better understanding of the user journey, you'll have a complete picture of what kind of content your audience needs at each step of their journey to help them make a decision. </p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="references">References<a class="hash-link" href="#references" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h4><p>Winters, S. (05 December 2019). What is Content Design? Content Design London.</p><p>Found on Twitter. Content precedes design quote. <a href="https://twitter.com/zeldman/status/804159148?s=20" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://twitter.com/zeldman/status/804159148?s=20</a></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Patricia McPhee</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/patriciamcphee</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="technical writing" term="technical writing"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Single sourcing and content reuse]]></title>
        <id>/2022/02/05/single-sourcing</id>
        <link href="https://patriciamcphee.github.io/portfolio/blog/2022/02/05/single-sourcing"/>
        <updated>2022-02-05T11:41:21.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Draft]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><strong>Draft</strong></p></blockquote><p>Single sourcing is a simple idea but misunderstood. People often think that single sourcing means that the online help and user manuals must be identical in terms of content. This is an incorrect assumption. Single sourcing is creating a single content source then producing different types of documentation from it. Single sourcing considers the differing needs of the audience and the strengths and weaknesses of each of your output media (Darley, p. 3).</p><p>In a nutshell, single sourcing is just a development strategy that enables writers to develop centralized information modules then map them to distinct audiences, media, or both without recreating the content for the other document formats. For example, you can map the content to your online help, website, marking material, user's guides, and training manuals with single sourcing. Another advantage to single sourcing is that the other document formats (i.e., online help and printed media) are automatically updated when you update the information module.</p><p>For technical writers, single sourcing means modular writing and information mapping. For example, rather than developing information for a given format, such as a user's guide or online help, writers develop information modules at the element level (i.e., section, paragraph, and sentence). The information modules get mapped to preselected audiences and media.</p><h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="references">References:<a class="hash-link" href="#references" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h4><p>Darley, J. (12 January 2003). Single Sourcing - An Introduction. Middlesex: Cherryleaf Ltd.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Patricia McPhee</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/patriciamcphee</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="creative writing" term="creative writing"/>
        <category label="technical writing" term="technical writing"/>
        <category label="single sourcing" term="single sourcing"/>
        <category label="content reuse" term="content reuse"/>
        <category label="draft" term="draft"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[4 Qualities of a Great How-To Video (blog draft)]]></title>
        <id>/2020/01/04/four-qualities-every-good-explainer-video-needs</id>
        <link href="https://patriciamcphee.github.io/portfolio/blog/2020/01/04/four-qualities-every-good-explainer-video-needs"/>
        <updated>2020-01-04T11:41:21.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Let's face it, everyone likes learning something new. Your audience is a curious bunch, no matter who they are, which is why how-to/explainer videos are perfect for any target audience. These videos are short, engaging breakdowns of broader concepts or tasks. They are also one of the most effective ways to quickly show viewers a big idea or how to do something. How-to/explainer videos must be easy to consume and to achieve this, the information delivered must be clear.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let's face it, everyone likes learning something new. Your audience is a curious bunch, no matter who they are, which is why how-to/explainer videos are perfect for any target audience. These videos are short, engaging breakdowns of broader concepts or tasks. They are also one of the most effective ways to quickly show viewers a big idea or how to do something. How-to/explainer videos must be easy to consume and to achieve this, the information delivered must be clear.</p><p>A well-produced video can undoubtedly enhance the experience for your viewers, but a well-produced video takes planning to meet a high standard of quality and clarity. Many people begin without knowing where to start or realizing the extent of the work involved. Video production is not a simple matter of recording and pressing play when you're done. It takes several hours to make a few minutes of high-quality video. A few tasks in creating a well-produced video include planning, scriptwriting, recording the video, recording and editing the voiceover, and rendering. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="what-qualities-make-a-great-how-to-video">What qualities make a great how-to video?<a class="hash-link" href="#what-qualities-make-a-great-how-to-video" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>As you read this article, think about your own experience as a viewer. What did you find helpful and not so helpful about the video? Was the message clear, did it flow and stick to the intended message, and did it keep you engaged throughout? Most importantly, did you get what you needed out of the video, or did it waste your time, and you didn't get much out of it?  </p><p>The following four qualities guide you from planning to writing a solid script to recording your video and selecting a voiceover professional. </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="1-having-a-good-script-with-a-clear-message-matters">1. Having a good script with a clear message matters<a class="hash-link" href="#1-having-a-good-script-with-a-clear-message-matters" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>If you have a world-class product, a weak script sabotages your video, making it dull at best and confusing at worst. Always plan what you're going to say. It's easy to ramble when you record. Instead, have a plan.</p><blockquote><p>An excellent how-to video script takes work.</p></blockquote><ul><li><p><strong>Define your message.</strong> Start by making a creative brief to establish the audience, goals, problems, solutions, and the proper tone. Next, you'll want to start with the actual words. This is necessary to help tailor the message. Finally, be straightforward and confident in your message. Keep these things in mind when defining your message:</p><ol><li><p>Why the video, and what's your angle? Don't make a video for the fun of it. Know your goal because you're either filling in an information gap or expanding your viewer's knowledge. HOW are you making life easier for them?</p></li><li><p>Why will the viewer care? What are their pain points? What are they trying to solve?</p></li><li><p>Anticipate the viewer's questions and make sure they get answered.</p></li><li><p>What value will this provide to the viewer?</p></li><li><p>What should the viewer take away from this video? Your conclusion should have an impact. If your video is sharp up until a shrug of a closer, all your work will be for nothing. You shouldn't end with an overtly sales-based message, but instead, there should be a final takeaway.</p></li></ol></li><li><p><strong>Communicate your brand.</strong> If you're only mentioning features in your video, then you're just playing it safe. Your viewers want to know how things impact them. Even if it's common sense, tell the viewer about how your product or idea benefits <strong>them</strong>. Consider what you'd like to hear if "you" were the customer. You're positioning the product as the "Secret Sauce" to solve or prevent the problem. After putting in the secret sauce, explain "Why" it works.</p></li><li><p><strong>Work with a professional scriptwriter.</strong> The script is the video's message; it's what you want to tell and transmit in the video.
The writer helps "engage" the right audience and makes them want to learn more (and keep on watching). The writer also helps keep the video length at just the right size; the longer the video, the more view drops it's likely to have.</p></li></ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="2-high-quality-video-recordings">2. High-quality video recordings<a class="hash-link" href="#2-high-quality-video-recordings" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>You can record anything and everything on your screen, but it can end up as a not-so-great viewing experience. We get that not everyone uses the same  recording software, but here are a few things to ensure consistency for the best recording quality and viewing experience:</p><ul><li><p><strong>Set up your desktop recording area and your recording software.</strong> Do not record "full screen" because it can record at a "not-so-great" aspect ratio. For example, recording at 1280x720 may seem small, but it's considered HD, plus it's the recommended size for YouTube videos.</p><p> <img src="https://www.pscmdesigns.com/images/16-9-ratio.png" alt="16:9 ratio"> </p><blockquote><p><strong>Tip!</strong> You can make a 1280 x 720px placeholder image for your desktop and then re-size any browser or application within the white space before you
start to record.</p></blockquote></li><li><p><strong>Recording workflow and tips.</strong> We want a smooth transition during mouse movements and screen changes so that no further editing is needed during postproduction.</p><ol><li><p>De-clutter and clean up your desktop.</p></li><li><p>Close unused applications.</p></li><li><p>Turn off notifications and disable pop-ups.</p></li><li><p>Open the application you want to record and then do a couple of practice walkthroughs of precisely what you want to show your viewers. This helps with smooth cursor motions, and, in the end, there's more minor editing to do for the video production specialist.</p></li><li><p>When you're ready to record, start the recording and follow these tips:</p><ul><li><p><strong>Watch your mouse cursor.</strong> You'll use it to show the viewer where to follow along while explaining things. It's essential, so make sure you make it as helpful as possible.</p><ul><li><p><strong>Don't circle things.</strong> Moving your mouse around as if you're talking with your hands leaves your viewers confused and unsure of where they should look. Instead, move it deliberately and with purpose.</p></li><li><p><strong>Don't move it at the speed of light.</strong> If you're moving your mouse across the screen too fast, your audience struggles to follow along and, ultimately, stops watching.</p></li><li><p><strong>If you can, try to cut out mistakes and unneeded content</strong>. Mistakes happen to the best of us. You'll be recording, and your mouse moves to the wrong place, you click the wrong thing, or something unexpected happens. It's okay – it's fixable.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Allow 5 seconds of silence before beginning your tutorial</strong> (following along with the script). This allows a buffer, so you don't cut off anything you meant to record on the screen.</p></li><li><p><strong>As you record, speak in a conversational tone (following the script),</strong> as if you were training someone sitting next to you. Be straightforward with your language. Take your time to say WHAT you're doing and WHY you're doing it. Then, let the actions speak for themselves.</p><p>Talking as you record helps with the smooth transition and stays at a pace that you would typically see in a one-on-one training session. Plus, when you speak following along with the script, the professional voiceover can be efficiently timed with the actions. Don't worry about fumbling over your words because your audio is edited out during postproduction.</p><blockquote><p><strong>Tip!</strong> If you go off-script, but it's a valuable tidbit for the user, the voiceover professional can modify the script.</p></blockquote></li><li><p><strong>Allow 5 seconds of silence at the end of the recording</strong>. Here you want to make sure you don't cut anything off.</p></li></ul></li></ol></li></ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="3-utilize-a-voiceover-professional">3. Utilize a voiceover professional<a class="hash-link" href="#3-utilize-a-voiceover-professional" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The quality of the narration makes a big difference in the overall quality of your video. Let's face it, folks, lousy narration turns off viewers faster than almost anything else. So, the importance of a clear and articulate voice in visual content is undeniable. If you want to reach a broad audience and keep them engaged, the narration must be excellent. You can ruin webinars and presentations by using the wrong voice. As a result, viewers turn their attention to the voice behind the message.</p><p>Getting and keeping your viewers' attention is why you need professional voiceovers. They are persuasive and give the right rhythm to your script. They train their voices for years and know how to make any communication exciting and easy to follow. Plus, they enjoy their jobs and smile, which can be heard in their voice and makes your video content more appealing. Professional voiceovers know how to control breath and rhythm so that the audience doesn't hear any disturbing pauses while listening.</p><p>An otherwise fantastic video is dead without the right voice to match the video's tone. Hire a professional whose sound resonates with your audience. Find someone specializing in the genre. You'd be surprised how many voiceover professionals specialize in a particular genre, such as technical or medical content. Professional voiceover is excellent, and (if you have the budget), bringing one in-house to record is always the best approach.</p><p>Your videos say a lot about your company and how you do business. And people tend to associate the quality of your content with the quality of your products or services.</p><blockquote><p>Source:
Professional Voice-Overs Are Essential For Your Video ....
<a href="https://www.daytranslations.com/blog/professional-voice-overs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.daytranslations.com/blog/professional-voice-overs/</a></p></blockquote><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="4-include-a-call-to-action">4. Include a call-to-action:<a class="hash-link" href="#4-include-a-call-to-action" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>People need a prompt, even if it's as simple as a nudge to visit the website or share it with colleagues.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_mojV" id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts<a class="hash-link" href="#final-thoughts" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>It's all about balance:</p><blockquote><blockquote><p><em>Explain; don't lecture.</em><br>
<em>Engage; don't bore.</em><br>
<em>Enchant; don't demand.</em></p></blockquote></blockquote>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Patricia McPhee</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/patriciamcphee</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="video-production" term="video-production"/>
        <category label="scriptwriting" term="scriptwriting"/>
        <category label="voiceover" term="voiceover"/>
    </entry>
</feed>