<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Patricia McPhee Blog</title>
        <link>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog</link>
        <description>Patricia McPhee Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 11:29:21 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Navigating the final lap: Crafting compelling release notes]]></title>
            <link>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog/2023/10/12/writing-effective-release-notes</link>
            <guid>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog/2023/10/12/writing-effective-release-notes</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 11:29:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Dive into the intricate art of crafting release notes, a pivotal element in the release cycle, and explore how to effectively communicate product enhancements and fixes.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Crafting the ultimate technical writer portfolio]]></title>
            <link>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog/2023/09/30/technical-writing-portfolio</link>
            <guid>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog/2023/09/30/technical-writing-portfolio</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2023 11:29:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[You can start by addressing the absence of formal or credible standards and best practices in the technical writing field at the beginning of your article. This would set the stage for the readers to understand the context and the significance of a well-crafted portfolio in demonstrating one's capabilities.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Elevating feature development]]></title>
            <link>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog/2023/09/18/elevating-feature-development</link>
            <guid>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog/2023/09/18/elevating-feature-development</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 11:29:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The quality of your input profoundly influences the quality of the output. In the context of features, a poorly defined one can undermine its value, affecting not just internal stakeholders but, more critically, end users.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The critical role of conversation design in an AI-driven world]]></title>
            <link>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog/2023/09/14/explore-the-role-of-conversation-design</link>
            <guid>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog/2023/09/14/explore-the-role-of-conversation-design</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 11:29:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In this digital age, communication has significantly evolved thanks to the advancements in artificial intelligence (AI). As we embrace the future, conversation design is emerging as a crucial aspect of communication. So, what exactly is conversation design, and how does it fit into the AI landscape?]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Information architecture and why it's important]]></title>
            <link>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog/2022/10/04/information-architecture</link>
            <guid>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog/2022/10/04/information-architecture</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 11:29:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[When we create something, we also need to describe how to use it. With information architecture, how we group and label things directly affect how easily the information can be found and used. Information architecture becomes even more important as the information available keeps growing. When faced with a lot of information, it becomes harder to sift through and find what you need.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How much does quality content matter?]]></title>
            <link>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog/2022/02/23/how-much-does-quality-content-matter</link>
            <guid>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog/2022/02/23/how-much-does-quality-content-matter</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 11:41:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The quality of your organization's technical documentation matters now more than ever. I have found in my experience that potential customers also evaluate the technical documentation carefully before they buy. Whether they're an IT professional evaluating an enterprise application or a consumer using a product, they're reading your content to learn about the product and how to use it.]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[4 Qualities of a Great How-To Video]]></title>
            <link>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog/2020/01/04/four-qualities-every-good-explainer-video-needs</link>
            <guid>https://www.patriciamcphee.com/blog/2020/01/04/four-qualities-every-good-explainer-video-needs</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2020 11:41:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Let's face it, everyone likes learning something new. Your audience is a curious bunch, no matter who they are, which is why how-to/explainer videos are perfect for any target audience. These videos are short, engaging breakdowns of broader concepts or tasks. They are also one of the most effective ways to quickly show viewers a big idea or how to do something. How-to/explainer videos must be easy to consume and to achieve this, the information delivered must be clear.]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>